Guide to the Noël J. Cortés Collection of French Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Noël J. Cortés Collection of French Manuscripts
1760-1927
GEN MSS 1173
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.43
(1 box)
Cortés, Nöel J.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by writer.
Noël J. Cortés, collector
Noël J. Cortés was born in Manila in 1907, and becamed a naturalized citizen of the United States in 1932. He was a medical doctor and lived in Philadelphia where he was affiliated with the Drexel Institute of Technology. He was a collector of manuscripts, books, and artworks.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of manuscript letters, writings, and documents, mostly in French, by writers, artists, historians, and philosophers, including Alexandre Dumas, Victor Hugo, Paul Morand, and George Sand.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from David J. Holmes on various funds, 1989-1997.
Artists -- France; Authors, French; France -- Social life and customs; Historians -- France; Artists -- France; Authors -- France; Historians -- France; Cortés, Nöel J.; Dumas, Alexandre, 1824-1895; Hugo, Victor, 1802-1885; Morand, Paul, 1888-1976; Sand, George, 1804-1876
- Carco, Francis, 1886-1957
  - "Mon ami Jou," autograph manuscript, signed, in French, with corrections, essay on the painter, Louis Jou., undated (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    With wrapper containing the bookplate of Dr. Noël J. Cortés.
- Dumas, Alexandre, 1824-1895
  - Autograph letter, signed, in French, to "Madame", undated (Box 1)
- Gautier, Judith, 1845-1917
  - Autograph letter, signed, in French, to "Cher ami", 1915 June 28 (Box 1)
    Letter laid in a copy of The Daughter of Heaven by Pierre Loti and Judith Gautier (New York: Duffield & Company, 1912), containing the bookplate of Herbert Boyce Satcher.
- Halévy, Ludovic, 1834-1908
  - Autograph letter, signed, in French, to "Monsieur", 1906 January 21 (Box 1)
- Hugo, Victor, 1802-1885
  - Autograph letter, signed, in French, to Barbey d'Aurevilly, 1860 October 6 (Box 1)
- [Knight, Richard Payne, 1751-1824]
  - Manuscript essay in Italian, believed to be in the hand of Knight, with English description of essay on verso of last page, "A very exact and curious account of the Pastoral life & Customs in abruzzo & Puglia--with reflections on the Worship of Priapus discovered to have existed in full force in the year 1780 at Isernia in Abruzzo & altho abolished at the time by H.S. [Majerty?] is still privately tolerated in that city--as I was informed by the Bishop's brother in the year 1795.", undated (Box 1)
- Marmontel, Jean François, 1723-1799
  - Autograph letter, signed, in French, to "Monsieur" [Voltaire?], 1760 August 5 (Box 1)
    With English typescript translation.
- Meissonier, Jean Louis Ernest, 1815-1891
  - 7 autograph letters, signed, in French, from Meissonier to various correspondents; 2 autograph letters, signed, in French, from Baron Michel de Intaigne; and 2 autograph notes, signed, in French, regarding transmittal of letters by Meissonier., 1863, 1882-1883, undated (Box 1)
- Montalembert, Charles Forbes, comte de, 1810-1870
  - Autograph letter, signed, in French, to an identified recipient, 1852 November 5 (Box 1)
    With typed transcription and translation.
- Morand, Paul, 1888-1976
  - "Fermé la nuit," page proofs, revised, with corrections, 1922 December (Box 1)
  - Autograph letter, signed, in English, on Hotel Pennsylvania, New York, stationery to T. R. Smith, 1927 March 25 (Box 1)
- Morings, A.
  - Autograph note, signed, in French, to M. Souiller, with attached receipt, 1797 March 6 (Box 1)
- Régnier, Henri de,1864-1936
  - Autograph letter, signed, in French, to "Mon cher ami", [1912 March?] (Box 1)
- Renan, Ernest, 1823-1892
  - Autograph letter, signed, in French, to "Cher Monsieur", 1863 June 27 (Box 1)
    With manuscript translation in an unidentified hand.
- Rolland, Romain, 1866-1944
  - Autograph letter, signed, in French, to "Cher Monsieur", 1920 January 3 (Box 1)
- Sand, George, 1804-1876
  - Autograph letter, signed, in French, to "Mon cher Monsieur" [Alexandre Ledru-Rollin?], undated (Box 1)
    With manuscript transcription and notes regarding George Sand on the stationery of Dr. Noël J. Cortés, and presumably in his hand.
- Stern, Daniel, 1805-1876
  - Autograph letter, signed, in French, to [Paul de Saint-Victor], 1859 March 24 (Box 1)
    With manuscript description in an unidentified hand.
- Symons, Arthur, 1865-1945
  - Autograph manuscript notes, signed, on John Wilmot, Earl of Rochester, with corrections, undated (Box 1)
- Wood, [Waite?]
  - Autograph letter, signed, in French, to [Du Glick?], 1779 April 29 (Box 1)
- Unidentified
  - Manuscript letter, in French, to "Monsieur & ami", 1794 February 23 (Box 1)